So any ideas
about the sakas
and the difference between saras
and tetana.
Mhm.
So what do you think is the difference?
SAS are involved with Avija. Mhm.
Chaitanas are more like free from a
but isn't can you have chitana without
it being a sankara? Because Sankara just
means um activity
or
doing. So how can you have
intention or choice without it being an
activity?
From my point of view,
I cannot step outside of my experience
as a whole and
see how would be would it be without
Avij.
Um so but what do you think it like how
what what do you have to remove? So
everybody recognizes that they have
saras in their experience. Now whether
that's chen or not we can put that aside
but what do you need to remove in order
for um
well can we but uh are we on the same
page about what we are talking about
when we use a sai to be right so I guess
we should verify that first so usually
it's understood as like um volitional
formations or
um various kinds of translations that
people have come up with And it usually
feels to people I think like it's it's
something that's not really my control.
It's uh something that gets removed kind
of indirectly by this practice that I do
that at some point gets rid of the
ignorance and uh somehow also gets rid
of the saras
but um
it's actually something that you are
active like it's a doing. Sankara means
doing and um in in kind of a
I because these are not like
philosophical terms that the Buddha was
using with some kind of grandiose
significance. It's if you if you read
like vic writings and stuff when they
use the word sankara
uh they were referring it to like the
the stuff that they would do like
rituals like uh things that they would
um organize
play out kind of do
and and not as some kind of I don't know
energies or something. So sankaras are
have to be seen in that practical sense
of things that that you are doing things
that you're responsible for. And so um
from that point of view
what would you have to remove
to um fix the problem with sarus
basically?
Dude, can you just step out of sankara
from the very beginning? No. So what is
the thing that you have to do then?
Understand what sankara are? Right. But
even even before that
the right. Yes. But even for
restraint it yeah in other words um you
have to recognize you you if you think
you can
kind of avoid them from the very
beginning uh you probably have a misconception of
uh you probably have a misconception of
what saras are. All you can do is uh
cultivate certain kinds of sankaras that
don't fuel ignorance.
So you have no choice but to do things
in other words but certain doings will
at least not fuel your ignorance
further. So that's the first step. You
have to recognize that there are
wholesome saras and unh wholesome saras.
Um and that yeah so that's that's the
practice of virtue
and then on the basis of that you can
get to understand what the sessation of
saras actually is. So when you have
established yourself in good sankara
quote unquote good actions then you can
understand the sessation of action
altogether. Um and that's the real u gist of it.
Um and that's the real u gist of it.
It's like it's it's not that you remove
ignorance and then you are left you kind
of go from sankara to chaitana because
as the Buddha said chetana is kama as
well. So and he also said sessation of
So and he also said sessation of
suffering is sensation of kama in other
words sessation of chit as well. So
um more accurately speaking uh sensation
of suffering is a sensation of all
activities or all doings or all
intentions as well. And sometimes even
the Buddha would say that um when there
is uh intention when there is chetana by
body speech and mind as a result of that
suffering arises.
So it's the sessation of all of that
that um constitutes actual freedom from
suffering. You cannot have saras or
chetana and at the same time not have
suffering. But uh of course now then the thing is
But uh of course now then the thing is
it's not a
like it can sound as if okay so
cessation of all action probably would
sound to most people as some kind of a
exotic state of just unconsciousness or
something but um it's it's something
that you have to actually develop.
It's uh and it's it's it's also
not something that happens to you. It's
something that you understand. So
literally the word understanding refers
to knowing something for yourself and
and knowing how you got there. Not just
oh I got this experience where there was
no doer, no no sense of self, but okay.
But what did you actually understood
understand there? That's what really
matters. And um
so
how then would you
or let's say first of all what is the
ignorance as a result of which there are sars
as a result of which there are sars
automatically?
What are you most
acutely not aware of? Instead of just
tell the five aggregates or some kind of
theoretical thing, what are you most
acutely not aware of because of which
you have some thoughts? There's something
There's something
that undermines my attention.
itself.
Yeah, you could put but that there will
be other factors. I think you could put
it that way. But even before you can go
in that direction, there's something
more even more acute that you need to
recognize something very simple.
There's a characteristic of Sankaraas
that's pretty much
like it's it's the only reason why they
can be there.
Take responsibility for my action. Uh
yes. But
how how would you what what is the
precondition for you to take
responsibility for an action?
A very simple answer. Precept. No, very
very very
direct thing. It's a it's it's almost
like a silly
um kind of question in a way, but you
realize actually it's not. Um
just be aware of myself. Well, yeah, be
aware that you're doing something to
begin with because that's the like it's
not um some unawareness of something. Uh
again like you can come up with all
sorts of explanations of unawareness of
three characteristics and this and that
but really most primarily when it comes
to uh sankaras you're unaware of them to
begin with. In other words you don't
recognize that you're actually doing
that thing. So yes, as you said, you the
the the first step toward doing anything
about it would be taking responsibility,
but to take responsibility for your
action, you need to know that it isn't
actually an action because it's not
going to feel like that initially. So um
because what we're talking about here is
not really just um
like unh wholesome sankaras by body and
speech because as we said that that
would have to be abandoned beforehand.
So these are now things that having
developed that uh having developed the
good Saras as I as I said before um to
replace the badas
uh you wouldn't even be aware
that uh that that those saras are things
that you're doing.
So which includes mental action. Yeah,
it well most primarily it it converges
in at that point basically because even
when somebody goes into complete state
of just vegetable or something uh that's
the part that can never go away. Yeah.
On some level if you are alive
um there is some degree of activity and
that's actually already a good
contemplation to just ask yourself like
mental action. So instead of just
agreeing, oh yeah, there's body, speech,
and mind, so there must be mental
action. But can I make a list of things
that that I've been mentally doing
mentally doing in the last hour, and
you'll find that it is remarkably
difficult because you you just
completely take for granted that action
pertains to to well, let's say body and
speech, and you think, well, what's in
here is happening to me. But no, it's
not like that. It's actually very it's
it's a very common thing that that
people would think that the daydreaming
kind of happens by itself or something
and then they they kind of need to shut
it down by um watching their breath or
something. And uh actually all that is
rooted in just not seeing that that is
something that you're doing because if
if I if I don't know if you're
jumping and then you want to stop
jumping do you have to watch your breath
in order to stop jumping? No, you stop
jumping. So the same thing is on the
mental level exactly the same principle
but because the person hasn't developed
themselves sufficiently in restraining
the actions of body and speech and the
action of the mind feels like it's
nebulous thing that almost doesn't
exist. Some people would even say that
their their thoughts are not real or
something. Um so
it's actually like that's the first step
you need to actually recognize oh I am
actually doing this and uh all of the
prerequisites of the gradual training
are geared towards making that apparent
like um you know having developed
yourself in the precepts and sensor
restraint and all these things when
you're in seclusion
um it would become very hard to ignore
obviously for a while, not just like one
day or something. But if you that
becomes your mo your lifestyle, uh it
would be very hard not to become aware
that the daydreaming is actually
something that you're doing. Because
even if in the beginning it feels like
it's coming by itself, once you've been
left alone for a while and haven't been
distracting yourself, you will start to
realize actually I am I am kind of
feeling actively fueling this and and
when it stops I restarted and I and I
kind of I'm I'm literally responsible
for it and uh then you start to see oh
actually that is a sankara that it was
arising solely because I was ignorant of
it and fur furthermore
uh also if you want to take the textbook
definition it's uh also ignorance of the
four noble truths. So all sankara is
ultimately kind of um
even if it's not a coarse kind it's
going to it's going to be coming out of
craving and so not seeing that it is
actually painful not seeing that it is
actually like you project it onto
like you project it onto
the objective of your daydreaming like
the thing I want to get or the thing I
want to get rid of or whatever.
and you kind of carry the view that
that's the like not having accomplished
that is the reason for your pain.
Ignoring the fact that it's the craving
right then and there that's actually
causing the pain. So not seeing the
craving is suffering gives rise to that
sara automatically.
So it it's it doesn't have to be that oh
I believe that I have to solve this
problem or something. No, it's just
ignoring the fact that it's the craving
first of all that the craving is there
and second of all that it's the craving
that is the actual root of suffering.
Automatically you give rise to saras.
You try to why you're trying to resolve
the pain which if you realize oh
actually it's the craving
to resolve the pain not the pain that's
the suffering. what purpose would any
effort of doing
um have?
So that's why sessation of saras again
is not a a mystical thing. It's
literally just when um you don't have
any further need to get rid of pleasure
sorry to get rid of pain or pursue
pleasure. It's it's as concrete as that because
It's it's as concrete as that because
every sincara converges around that
converges around um not wanting to
endure whatever is there.
And so all the actions that were
previously tainted by craving by body
speech and mind would cease. Well, yeah.
action as a as a
as a as a phenomenon in of itself that
would have to seize as well because
I mean that's why even in the sut you
wouldn't you wouldn't see actually a
definition of saying that a narhat
uh kind of has a pure five aggregate or
something uh because that would mean
saying that they still have saras and
nibbana is a station of saras it's often
defined so so that would be a
contradiction but then you realize So
how can you have um
like like that's when you realize that
it's a very literal statement when the
Buddha says that it's not uh that it's
only Chetana that is the that is kama
you would think oh yeah of course but no
it's it it means that like physical
movements verbal movements even mental
movements in and of themselves are not
what kama is it's the
intending the kind of uh directing or uh
inclining towards things that is the the
kama if there's no inclining actually I
think there's a there's a s that says u
when one is dependent one is moved
when one is moved one inclines and as a
result of inclining there There is
coming and going. Yeah. And with coming
and going there is sickness, aging,
death. Um well, birth, sickness, aging,
death. Um so it's it's a it's that kind
of it's it's as simple as that. It's
not just like I decide to do something
and I kind of manifest it out into the
world. Initially, of course, it's going
to feel like that. And when you start
keeping the precepts and restraining
your actions, you're going to start to
see that that was kind of the very last
outpour of the river, like the last part
basically. But it's it's really just uh
um
inclining towards something having that
that kind of uh directionality
in your experience. And uh when
ignorance is abandoned again in the very
concrete terms when there is pleasure
and there is no directionality no
inclining towards needing to have more
of it
that that's then there's no china. If
there's no inclining towards needing to
have less pain there's no china.
And um
then uh then you could say okay well
it's it's it's
only to the extent that the
there will no there like nothing that
you would do would be rooted in like
that's factually when you would have no
self in the sense of an outside kind of thing
in the sense of an outside kind of thing
that's trying to puppeting puppet stuff
around to kind of get get what it wants.
But it see you arrive at it indirectly
through that non-inclinination
rather than like deciding beforehand
that you will deny your sense of control
rooted in your sense of control that
just wants to get rid of things. So it's
it's uh that sense of self, that sense
of I is a side effect of that
inclination to to control things rather
than being uh some kind of metaphysical
entity that that you destroy or
something. Mhm.
So then that's what's that that's what
you that's where you need to look for
the saras in relation to pleasure and
pain because that's where the activation
where the where the inclination comes to
be uh and uh in rel so in relation to
the things that you want to do that your
mind is pressured to do that's where you
calm the saras not in relation to kind
of everywhere nowhere
it's it's when you have contained
yourself by the precepts,
um you will naturally, whether you like
it or not, unless you're distracting
yourself with some kind of um oblivion
practice, you will start to notice that
your mind is inclining towards certain
things. It's inevitable. And uh that's
where you need to then start
understanding okay how do I cut this off
at the root rather than replacing it
with something else which is going to be
another activity or kind of thinking to
counter it or or just looking away.
All of those are going to be activities.
Instead, you need to find how do I go to
the very root of this whole inclination
of this whole movement of just trying
not trying to do something just trying
as a thing in itself. How do I cut that
off? And well, it's it's exactly through
what you said initially. It's through
the understanding of um dependent
origination quote unquote
where you kind of um by recognizing with
this this is you um
you you kind of remove any space
because of which you could assume that
you can do something about it because
all you see is this and this other thing
and then where is the space for me to
interfere in me.
And that's why it's so important to see
it as a simultaneous
um presence of two things cuz for as
long as it's like observing the one
thing coming and then the next one and
then the next one, it's going to be your
sense of self that's observing that. And
that observation in and of itself is an
activity. No matter how subtle it feels
like you thinking that you're seeing the
sequence of mind moments coming and
going that is an activity.
So we gave one example of
day saras which is practical which would
be daydreaming let's say um
thinking of course sensual thoughts
first thoughts so what would be another
can we come up with other examples of so
that it doesn't feel like an abstract
thing some cards that you'll be doing even
some cards that you'll be doing even
when you're already virtuous and and
established in a certain boundary of
conduct.
Wanting something. Mhm.
So what would be the solution to that?
Can you just uh cash and want anything?
Well, that's become what I want now.
Okay. So you have to start like that of
course otherwise you won't uh you won't
try and you will just um fall into some
sort of abstract idea of okay just don't
want anything and that's it. No you you
have to start with an activity. In other
words I I want to solve this because
there's a problem here.
But then how so what would be the
solution? Like how do you Yeah. I think
it's more kind of what you say like more
or less before is like instead of kind
of myself doing it like more like
discerning that actually
whether I like it or not I cannot want
things to be otherwise than they already
are because it's just me interfering
with what determine what I can interfere with
what determine what I can interfere with
which is kind of contradiction in
itself. So, so um
is it that
like what what what practically you
would what would you practically discern
let's say um you have wanting of some
even neutral kind how do you uh see that
that you cannot interfere because again
just telling yourself oh I cannot
interfere it might be accurate but
unless you actually see the fact that
like you put you you see it in such a
way that even if you wanted to interfere
you see that you can't. How are you able
to see that way?
Well, you kind of have to develop the
kind of recognition that I mean one of
the kind of foundation of mindfulness for
kind of foundation of mindfulness for
example like just recognizing that well
the body is like the basis on which I
can act and I can never step outside of
that regardless and just like not like
putting it in the front like just like
looking at looking at that but just
more recognizing like my whole
experience is defined by that and I can
never like actually get out of that as
you said at the beginning that's like
say like my experience as a whole is
defined by that regardless and just
keeping that in mind but let it sink not
like over rationalizing it but like just
letting pervade so to say. Yeah. So you
basically have to recognize that
even if you go and like you don't deny
that whatever it is your mind wants to
do that you qu do it because that would
be kind of just um
wishful thinking in in a way. No, it's
like that there is that possibility
there. But the fact is even if I were to
actually go and do it, would I ever step
outside of this foundation?
Actually, you realize no. And then from
that perspective
like you become clear oh even when I
let's say you take the foundation of
feeling even when I actually went and in
the past and engaged with sensuality and
pursued this and got angry with people
and got into fights and stuff. Did I
ever actually step outside of that
feeling that initially got me to act?
and you realize actually no it's it's
pretty much every time it actually even
got worse. So
if you just recognize that you see okay
yes I could act like I could go and do
this whatever but
from this perspective I'm not actually
moving anywhere
and that's when it ceases to be a
sankara I think we spoke about that at
some point like um it's a sankara not
because of the kind of movement of your
arms or something it's a sankara because
there's that assumption that you are
actually going somewhere else
where whereas you realize actually no
there's anything that's done would have
to remain exactly on the same level as
where I started from and then that's
what I mean like even if you were to go
and do it you don't deny that there is
that possibility it's like as far as you
would possibly be able to go you will
never be able to step outside you will
never actually be able to go anywhere
and that's where that suta um where the
Buddhist says like u the the world is to
be known within the confines of this um
fenom long body and it's it's the
sensation of the world is found there as
well. So in other words,
there is nothing outside of it and
anywhere that you would go, you still
remain in that same body like and and
when you as you said before when when
you're daydreaming when you're having
kind of unh wholesome thoughts even
about this or that instead of just
replacing it with another kind of
daydreaming because that's that's a
funny thing like you you would kind of
imply that if if I'm focusing on some on
some specific object magically that
isn't daydreaming anymore, but actually
just because it's kind of more moving
less or something, but it's exactly
still the same assumption of movement,
the same assumption of going somewhere
else. Instead,
you go the other way and you recognize
you undermine the whole possibility and
you see it doesn't matter what I do. It
doesn't matter what I attend to. Doesn't
matter whether I sit, stand, walk or lie
down. I'm not actually going anywhere.
And that's that's uh in a way that's
probably even an unpleasant recognition
if if especially if you're not developed
in virtue because it's like uh being
confined and realizing like well
yeah again like it's it's not even a
matter of I am deciding to calm my mind
or something. It's like even if I were
to ignore this and go back or or
whatever, I won't ever that recognition
will go. I won't ever actually be able
to get outside of this. So you're
properly cornered basically. Yeah.
But at the same time, it is also the
most relieving thing of all because you
realize like, oh, so I don't even have
to do what I assumed the practice was.
Mhm. like like go here and do this and
think about this and remove this or do
that. No, it's actually the other
direction. It's recognizing that you
can't even
change anything even if you want to.
Mhm. But before that, in order to arrive at
But before that, in order to arrive at
that point, you like I said before, you
need to have tried and strived and done
things on that level of virtue, restraint and
on that level of virtue, restraint and
stuff because otherwise you will just be
misconceiving what saras are based on
whatever assumptions and views you carry
and you won't be seeing it concretely in
that um yon so sense. Mhm. like right
here what am I actually doing
the imposing whatever you read or heard
or thought or reflected saras are into
your experience and then that's anything
that comes out of that is just going to
be another sara
I think even yeah actually we get a
simile of like Um
when he referred to that's the word that
people translate is like how to stop
thinking he said um how do you
he said um how do you
calm the activity the sankara of
thinking and he said um it's like a
person who is running recognizes why am
I running what if I walk then after
walking for a while they recognize why
am I walking what if I stand and then it
goes all the way down to okay so why am
I sitting let me lie down and then you
realize the whole principle there is
that the sankara is something that the
person becomes aware of like they were
previously unaware of they weren't
realizing it and once they recognize it
they're able to uh kind of
calm it or or tranquilize it quote
unquote and then abide in a more refined
um type of activity. And that's the
whole principle like it's if you don't
recognize it, if you don't see exactly
what it is that if you don't see that
the whole thing is actually coming from
you, it's not being imposed by your mind
kind of working on its own or something.
It's you choosing to engage with these
things that present themselves
and nobody else can come in between.
It's you alone. If you don't see that,
anything you try to do is still going to
be within the same.
Yeah. So what you say like now is like
as long as someone doesn't recognize
like this principle like to the full
extent. He basically didn't take took
responsibility fully as still kind of
assume that something happened to. Yeah.
Exactly. So it's it's uh like that is
why it is fully
uh
like nothing can like fully reversible
because if it were that something you
kind of concocted and it just came up
you you develop this thing and then it
sort of stays there for a while
inherently that's going to be
impermanent. But if it's you
recognizing, oh, I was actually doing
this stuff. Let me now stop.
Then who can actually even if like you
let's say you were running and and
somebody puts a gun to your head and
says start running again. Well, he can't
actually force you to run. It would be
you who would make a choice. Yeah. Not
to die and run instead. So nobody can
force you to do anything. And in the
same way nobody can force you to engage
or or to uh do sankaras. Nobody can
force you to have craving. Yeah.
Not even mara as the suta said like when
he was trying to provoke the Buddha
because he said well I own the eye. I
own the ear. I own the all of the six
senses. And then the Buddha said yes
that's true.
He didn't say he didn't say oh you're
wrong about that. He said no that that's
factually correct but um there is an
escape from that which you don't
understand
now is taking responsibility an activity
it's a fault. So I think yes.
Mhm. So is that something that in the
end can also go to the sessation of
sankara?
Yeah. Because I think there is a
difference in between like taking
responsibility and discerning
responsibility because taking taking
because taking taking
already implies
something you did with the verb taking
but if you realize well I am responsible
like the same principle I am responsible
even if I don't want to be responsible
then it's not you taking responsibility
and ironically that recognition frees
you from the burden of responsibility
because the only reason responsibible
ability was a burden is because you
thought you still imply that it was
possible to avoid it.
And uh that's the the principle with
with everything like you don't actually
fix what you think the problem is. You
simply realize that there was no need to
fix it in the first place
in terms of getting rid of pain and
getting rid of of um uh or or pursuing
pleasure. Of course, initially, like I
said, it is a problem if you're engaging
in certain actions like breaking the
precept because as much as you might
want to tell yourself through fancy
ideas that uh you can do that without
craving, you are actually taking up the
entire spectrum of experience just by
doing any of those things. Mhm.
So what would be another
very pertinent sara that would be there when
pertinent sara that would be there when
you give up let's say the all these past
saras of um let's say you the person is
taking the precepts and uh bodily,
verbally, and even mentally. They don't
engage with sensuality, aversion, or
distraction. That of course doesn't mean that they're
That of course doesn't mean that they're
pure already because
then it would take one day to have gone
around. Um, so what is left there that's still
Um, so what is left there that's still
not quite rained in
isn't it like the same principle like I
am doing all this like I am the one like
holding this precept holding this virtue
holding this sense strength and there
will be a result out of it like I'm
expecting these things that is that is
the what it kind of boils down to, but
more specifically, what what is the kind
of uh
what would be the thing that you're
still doing when
merely having restrained yourself from
course? Mhm. Behaviors,
you would still be kind of
wound up there would be hindrances for
example. Sure. Or just the expectation
that there's still something to get that
you do not have. Right. Yeah. Exactly.
But what is it that you would be trying
to get if you don't have?
Well, you think that you can get peace
if the feeling which is not present is
otherwise for example. That's that's
basically Yeah. So then you realize
or or still you would still carry the
assumption that uh the solution to all
of this is to replace Mhm. whatever
pressure is there with something else.
Yeah. And uh for that reason alone
you're suffering like it's the craving.
It's not what you thought you had to
resolve. It's always the craving. Mhm.
And that's why the Buddha said uh even
in the like in the satiphatana
contemplation he said um when there's a mind with
he said um when there's a mind with
greed
he said you know the mind of greed is a
mind we with greed and it says through
that practice you abide disengaged not
seeking up anything in the world he
doesn't say that he replaces the minor
greed with something else Mhm. And
because again that would be taking it
up. You you you abandon the mind of
greed simply to the extent that you
don't act out of it. Yeah. But then now
if you also carry the opposite activity
of still to some tiny extent expecting
that it shouldn't be there which is part
of the greed actually. Yeah. That
expectation that that partakes in the
same thing. Yeah. And uh ironically then
through the craving like it's because of
the craving that that greed is there. So
by fueling the craving whether it's
towards or against you're fueling the
basis for greed. And so even if even if
you did actually
get rid of it somehow
through whatever means
the fact that you still cultivated
craving that's precisely what's going to
make it arise again. even if all you
feel victorious or whatever because you
succeeded in in removing it. Um that's
still pretty much the same principle of
sensuality like I just
have this thing push it away with
something better and feel satisfied as a
result of that.
that it is it is quite a hard thing for
people to accept because all the views
are about countering and finding a quick
solution for the for for the problem and
uh then you don't realize actually that
middle way that the Buddha described
is a much more subtle thing than just
like oh don't don't be too kind of
aesthetic and don't be too indulgent
either. Of course that's the
broad kind of principle that you'll be able to
kind of principle that you'll be able to
recognize externally. But even that the
Buddha because the Buddha said well some
of his disciples would be eating once
every three days and the other ones
would be eating food from the king every
day. Uh so and wearing silk rub and
whatnot. So even on that level you can't
quite say that it's it's just a external
predefined um type of conduct. It is most secularly
um type of conduct. It is most secularly
on that internal level whether you kind
of um
engage with the bad saras
or you engage with the good ones which
is the good sankara is the sankara of
trying to get basically trying to get
rid of your sensuality trying to get rid
of your aversion through that sense of
like I want something else I want this
to go away which eventually also has to
cease. Yeah. Yeah. So that's the that's
the um
all of the the the times the Buddha
would describe like oh the tuning of the
strings um the the how do you crush the flood?
um the the how do you crush the flood?
It's it's by not pushing forward by not
standing still. Uhhuh. So all of that
converges around that principle like you
push forward. Well it's it's well
initially let's say you're not even
pushing forward. You're just
letting it carry carry you away. And
that's your initial state of of
everybody as a householder. Just just
give in. Just go with the flow. Just
just go with it. And then of course you
unless you fight it, you won't be able
to establish the basis for the middle
way, which is the precepts. But at a
certain point, you have to realize,
wait, now I need to learn how to drop
this without going back to just not
doing anything at all and letting the
flood carry me. Mhm. So without doing
either, that's the that's the sensation of
that's the that's the sensation of
suffering.
And that's basically what sided paramasa
is like. It's not a not a
thing that's just hidden somewhere in
your subconscious.
It is like um something that will
actually be present quite frequently.
It's like a that tendency to kind of
literally hold on to the sense of duty
of like I need to get rid of this. I
need to kind of just going beyond
you were at the at the right point like
you just gave up. You you stopped
engaging with sensuality but you keep
carrying it further into like out of out
of just that sense of duty. It doesn't
have to be anything specific just so
that momentum has to cease as well
basically. Yeah. not discerning that
actually I I I already did what I had to
do and then I just keep winding myself
up by assuming that there's something
more and then overlooking just by
overlooking the fact that oh I I was
actually right right where I had to be.
Mhm. Then you just keep going elsewhere.
Yeah. Because probably it felt sort of
dissatisfying or unpleasant. So you
think there's more to be done rather
than to just and and that's that goes
back to what I said. It's like
any sense of what you might assume is
what you need to resolve is just going
to be a distraction from the what the
actual problem is which is right now I
am craving against something. Mhm.
If if there's any sense of like oh doubt
and asking myself oh what is it what is
it and and feeling overwhelmed or
something all of that can only be
because I'm overlooking something that
should in a way be obvious.
It's not because of the kind of built of
ignorance, but you realize actually it's
it's right there.
It's it's not as kind of clearly defined
as what I'm used to seeing like objects
out there in the world. But it is
factually I am feeling like this. If
somebody were to come and ask me like
how do you feel, you would get the
answer. Mhm. And right there in relation
to that ambiguous feeling, you are
trying to get rid of it. And that's the
problem. There cannot be anything else.
Mhm. that that causing you suffering.
So it's just drilling that in because
you might recognize for a moment but
then the assumption will set back in and
you will continue then trying to find
the answer and resolve it and and
somehow through different ways. It's not
always going to be the same um solution
that you're going to be striving for,
but the common thread is you're looking
for something and that's the problem.
Doesn't matter whether you incline up,
down, left, right, front or back. The
point is that inclination in and of
itself is what causes birth, aging,
death. on what I said before.